Guide to the William Blathwayt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1646-1796; Series I; 4.0' (10 boxes)
  - Yard, Robert
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1698 Nov 22
      Possible prorogation of Parliament if William III does not return before Nov 29; report on Irish Parliament. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Parliament, 1698. 3. Ireland. Parliament, 1698.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1698 Nov 29
      Parliament prorogued until 6 December; Norris made a baronet. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Parliament, 1698. 3. Norris, William, Sir, 1657-1702.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1698 Dec 2
      Lords Justices advise against shipping corn to Flanders; candidates for Speaker; report on Irish Parliament; sailing of Benbow with the West Indies squadron. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Parliament, 1698. House of Commons. 3. Ireland. Parliament, 1698. 4. Great Britain. Navy. 5. Benbow, John, 1653-1702.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 1 (Box 10, Folder 208)
      First letter in a series of reports to Blathwayt on English political matters. Blathwayt was accompanying William III on the continent as secretary of war and private secretary.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 4
      Sir George Rooke has sailed to Spithead. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 8
      Report on meeting of Lords Justices about a new governor of New England, with memorials presented by both Sir Henry Ashurst and Col. Dudley; five Dutch ships wanted for English fleet. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Dudley, Joseph, 1647-1720. 3. Ashurst, Henry, Sir, 1645-1711. 4. Great Britain. Navy.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 11
      Forwarding Sir Henry Ashurst memorial against Col. Dudley. 1. Dudley, Joseph, 1647-1720. 2. Ashurst, Henry, Sir, 1645-1711.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 11 (Box 10, Folder 208)
      Writing on behalf of Lord Abercorn who wishes the title of Strabone in the Irish peerage. 1. Abercorn, James Hamilton, 8th Earl of, 1661-1734.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 15
      Lords Justices wish to know the King's pleasure about proroguing Parliament. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 17
      Concerning a representation by Spanish merchants to the Admiralty to send a squadron of English war ships to Cadiz to bring back "effects" worth £500,000. Accompanied by a holograph copy of Yard's letter. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Admiralty. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Spain.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 17
      Yard's explanations about the representation of the Spanish merchants (headed by Sir John Houblon) and the fears of the Lords Justices of provoking the large French fleet off Cadiz by sending British men of war. 1. Houblon, John, Sir, d. 1712. 2. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- France. 5. Great Britain. Admiralty.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 18
      Lords Justices have directed the Admiralty to order a frigate or two to cruise near the Islands of Jersey and Guernsey; sailing of Capt. Whetstone's fleet for West Indies. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Admiralty. 3. Whetstone, William, Sir, d. 1711.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Jul 22 (Box 10, Folder 208)
      Lords Justices have directed the Admiralty to provide transportation for the two regiments to be sent from Ireland to the West Indies. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Admiralty.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 1
      Sending news of the further prorogation of Parliament; Rochester's departure for Ireland, and Killigrew's petition for support. 1. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701. 2. Rochester, Laurence Hyde, 1st Earl of, 1641-1711. 3. Killigrew, Henry, d. 1712.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 5
      Rooke and the Spanish flota; Rochester's departure delayed. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 3. Rochester, Laurence Hyde, 1st Earl of, 1641-1701.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 5
      Sir George Rooke's attendance before Lords Justices about the possible expedition to Cadiz. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 5
      Asking Blathwayt to help his nephew James Foulkes get a captaincy in Sir Charles O'Hara's regiment. 1. Great Britain. Army. 2. Tyrawley, Charles O'Hara, 1st Baron, 1640?- 1724. 3. Foulkes, James.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 8 (Box 10, Folder 208)
      Addresses from the Grand Juries of Hampshire (headed by Col. Norton) and Bucks (headed by Sir Richard Temple) presented to the Lords Justices. 1. Norton, Richard, d. 1732. 2. Cobham, Richard Temple, Viscount, 1675-1749. 3. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 4. Trevor, Thomas Trevor, Baron, 1658-1730.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 8
      Departure of Capt. Delavall to redeem the captives in Barbary; other news. 1. Delavall, George, d. 1723. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Morocco.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 12
      Brig. Selwyn received his orders this day to accompany Whetstone's squadron to the West Indies. 1. Selwyn, William. 2. Whetstone, William, Sir, d. 1711. 3. Great Britain. Navy.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 15
      Rooke and the Cadiz expedition; Selwyn and Whetstone's West Indies squadron; Delavall and the Barbary captives; Lord Justices wish the King to decide soon on the new governor for New England. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 2. Selwyn, William. 3. Delavall, George, d. 1723. 4. Dudley, Joseph, 1647-1720. 5. Great Britain. Lords Justices.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 19
      Sailing of Rooke; other naval news. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 22
      The Lords Justices desire the King's approbation for their order for the sailing of the fleet; they also wish advice about ships to meet to Spanish flota. 1. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Houblon, John, Sir, d. 1712.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 26
      Rooke and the Fleet; English merchants in Florence; news from Beeston in Jamaica. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Blackwell, Lambert, Sir, d. 1727. 4. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Tuscany. 5. Beeston, William, Sir, fl. 1702.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Aug 29
      Rooke and the Fleet; the Bishop of Hereford's death. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 2. Ironside, Gilbert, Bishop of Hereford, 1632-1701.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 2 (Box 10, Folder 209)
      Proroguing of Parliament; state of regiments in the West Indies. 1. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701. 2. Great Britain--Colonies--West Indies. 3. Whetston, William, Sir, d. 1711. 4. Selwyn, William.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 5
      Account of Lord Bath's suicide; news of the fleet. 1. Bath, John Brenville, Earl of, 1629-1717. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 9
      Acknowledging the King's orders about the Spanish flota. 1. Great Britain. Navy.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 10
      Outlining the orders which the Lord Justices sent to the various squadrons of the Navy. 1. Great Britain. Navy.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 12
      Damage to one of Benbow's ships. 1. Great Britain. Navy. 2. Benbow, John, 1653-1702.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 16
      Prorogation of Parliament; account of the movements of the fleet. 1. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 18
      Movements of the fleet. 1. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 2. Benbow, John, 1653-1702. 3. Whetstone, William, Sir, d. 1711. 4. Delavall, George, d. 1723.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 23
      Movements of the fleet. 1. Great Britain. Navy. 2. Rooke, George, Sir, 1650-1709. 3. Benbow, John, 1653-1702.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 26
      Having received reports that the French and Spanish intend to prevent any commerce by the English and Dutch, the Lords Justices wish to send instructions to Benbow and word of warning to the plantations; Spanish flota. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- France. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Spain. 3. Benbow, John, 1653-1702. 4. Great Britain-- Colonies--West Indies. 5. Houblon, John, Sir, d. 1712.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Sep 30 (Box 10, Folder 209)
      Describes the presentation of an address from the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Common Council of London to the Lords Justices concerning the French declaration about the pretended Prince of Wales; Spanish flota; need for better relations with Bavaria; Stoughton petition to be governor of New England. 1. London. Corporation. Court of Common Council. 2. Levett, Richard, Sir, d. 1711. 3. Houblon, John, Sir, d. 1712. 4. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Bavaria. 5. Stoughton, Anthony.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 2
      Account of the poll for the Lord Mayor of London, at which Sir William Gore was elected; report of a meeting of the East India Company, at which they debated forming a third company. Only the last part of the letter is in Yard's hand. 1. London. Lord Mayor--Elections. 2. Gore, William, Sir, d. 1707. 3. East India Company (English).
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 3
      Fairborne's squadron will sail to Holland; Whetstone has reached Kinsale. 1. Fairborne, Stafford, Sir, d. 1742. 2. Whetstone, William, Sir, d. 1711. 3. Great Britain. Navy.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 7
      Fairborne has been delayed by contrary winds; Sir Joseph Jekyll's report on a woman hanged for murdering her bastard child, but she was cut down too soon and revived-- should she be hanged again? 1. Fairborne, Stafford, Sir, d. 1742. 2. Jekyll, Joseph, Sir, 1663-1738
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 10 (Box 10, Folder 209)
      List of the ships in the King's Convoy; news of addresses against the French. 1. Great Britain. Navy. 2. Fairborne, Stafford, Sir, d. 1742. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--France.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 14
      Response of gratitude for the City of London's address; storm damage to Whetstone's squadron; prerogation of parliament. 1. London. Corporation. Court of Common Council. 2. Houblon, John, Sir, d. 1712. 3. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701. 4. Great Britain. Lords Justices.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 17
      Orders for the West Indies squadron. 1. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Great Britain--Colonies--West Indies.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 21
      Orders for the West Indies squadron. 1. Great Britain. Navy. 2. Benbow, John, 1653-1702.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 24
      Orders for the West Indies squadron; prorogation of Parliament. 1. Great Britain. Navy. 2. Great Britain--Colonies--West Indies. 3. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 28
      Prorogation of parliament. 1. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1701 Oct 31
      Prorogation of Parliament; Munden and the ships under his command. 1. Great Britain. Parliament, 1701. 2. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 3. Munden, John, Sir, d. 1719. 4. Great Britain. Navy.
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Includes fragment in Latin about the succession of the King of France; fragment in Italian; note stating that, "The Charge of Bread, Waggons, Hospitalls, and Contingencies is not here sett down as being supposed to be included in the E. of Ranelagh's accompt;" fragment in Dutch; quotation from Sir Richard Baker, A Chronicle of the Kings of England, 3rd edition, p. 486., 1692. n.d. (Box 10, Folder 210)
- Diplomatic Papers, 1666-1703; Series II; 0.25' (1 box)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1666 (Box 11, Folder 211)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1667 (Box 11, Folder 212)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1668 (Box 11, Folder 213)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1669 (Box 11, Folder 214)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1670 (Box 11, Folder 215)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1671 (Box 11, Folder 216)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1672 (Box 11, Folder 217)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1673 (Box 11, Folder 218)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1678 (Box 11, Folder 219)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1681 (Box 11, Folder 220)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1681-82 (Box 11, Folder 221)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1682 (Box 11, Folder 222)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1683 (Box 11, Folder 223)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1698 (Box 11, Folder 224)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1699 (Box 11, Folder 225)
    Includes commission for Sir Francis Vere
  - Diplomatic papers, 1700 (Box 11, Folder 226)
  - Diplomatic papers, 1703 (Box 11, Folder 227)
  - Diplomatic papers, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 228)
  - Accounts, 1691-1703 (Box 11, Folder 229)
  - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 230)
- Oversize, 1667-1714; 1.5' (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from Series I and II. The papers from Series I are alphabetically arranged and those from Series II chronologically arranged. Box 12, folder 248 holds Restricted Fragile Papers that may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Address
      - "An Addresse of a Commoner of this Nation.. .", [ca. 1667] (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 231)
    - Backwell, Edward, d. 1683
      - 3 documents relating to the disputed election in Wendover, Bucks, [1673] (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 232)
    - Boselli, Galeazzo, Conte
      - ALS (in Italian) to William III, Bastile, 1701 Mar 12 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 233)
    - Chester, England
      - "Present State of the Stores at Chester," Chester, 1688/9 Feb 1 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 234)
    - Dartmouth, George Legge, 1st Baron of, 1648-1691?
      - Memorandum, holograph: "Warrents for his Highnessthe Prince of Orange's signing," n.p, [1688/9 Jan] (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 235)
    - Faria, Juan de
      - "Informacion que haze Juan de Faria", [1680] (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 236)
    - Great Britain. Navy
      - "An Account of the Victualling of the Fleet", 1693 Jun 30 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 237)
    - Great Britain. Sovereigns, etc. 1689-1694
      - "Draught of a Declaration ag[ains]t Lodging of Soldiers in private houses", 1688/9 Jan 5 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 238)
    - Great Britain. Treasury
      - "Scheme concerning the Expence & Funds of the Civil List", 1713/14 Feb 4 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 239)
    - Memorials
      - "Memorial of the Spanish Ambassador to the States", 1693 Oct 7 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 240)
    - Saxony (Electorate, 1356-1806) Laws, statutes, etc.
      - 3 documents relating to the Electorate of Saxony, 1693 Mar 13-May 1 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 241)
    - Scotland. Privy Counci
      - Orders for Danish troops in Scotland, 1689 Oct 30, Dec 16 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 242)
  - DIPLOMATIC PAPERS
    - Diplomatic papers, 1669 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 243)
    - Diplomatic papers, 1670 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 244-45)
    - Diplomatic papers, 1682 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 246)
    - Diplomatic papers, n.d. (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 247)
  - RESTRICTED FRAGILE PAPERS
    - Restricted fragile papers, 1703, n.d. (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 248)